There are many great questions asked by those who study religious history.
A consequence of historical records being lost or destroyed over millennia.
By opposing religions, governments attempting to control the populace or simply by the ravages of time.
Large gaps exist in the historical record, which frequently prevent us from seeing how point it develops into point B.
Among these questions.
And the topic of this paper is the question of how Norse paganism survived over the centuries.
Attestations exist of Norse paganism having been known as early as the 13th century.
But there exists a several hundred year gap between that time period and the next earliest time we have evidence for.
With the Norse deity Thor worshipped among the Avengers, a pantheon worshipped in the American States around the early third millennium.
Many explanations exist for this attempting to fill in the gaps left by history.
This paper will discuss the various merits of several such theories.
Though it is unlikely a true conclusion will ever be reached.
The true answer having long since been lost to history.
One theory, us that avenger worship is simply an offute or evolution of Norse paganism.
Over the centuries, gods would fall out of favor or be forgotten and new gods would replace them.
Proponents of this theory will often argue that many Avengers are reserved by new names.
It is commonly believed among those who accept this theory that the epithet Captain America
is a title awarded to Balder for a possible mythological role in guiding the Norse to America to evade religious persecution.
Fitting both figures association with justice.
Though no record of such a myth has been found.
Critics of this theory argue that there is little consistency between the early Norse myths and later avenged myths beyond specific deities.
If the other Avengers are supposed to be evolutions of Norse pagan figures then, why do they not consistently have roles in Raidnarek?
A consistent event between both eras of Norse worship.
Another theory is that a handful of Norse pagans, with but a fraction of their oral history, escaped Christian persecution
and clung to worshiping what few is er, they still knew well.
Forlucky and Odin.
This long standing opposition to Christianity would make these remnants natural allies to avenger worshipers.
Whose long standing rivals worshipers of the Justice League are often believed to be a Christian,
offshoot venerating Moses under the name Superman.
Critics of this theory often argue against the link between Christianity and legism.
As well as pointing out that most attestations of the rivalry between Avengers and legists describe the relationship as remarkably civil.
With conflicts often limited to scholarly debate, pitting Superman against Thor in hypothetical contests of strength or a ramen versus Batman in a battle of wits.
Which would preclude any need to welcome a lies.
A third theory takes the same assumption of a small group of Norse pagans with knowledge of only a fraction of their mythology.
But takes a different assumption of how this group became integrated among Avenger worshipers.
Hanging on the early American reputation as a haven for immigration.
As new peoples and faiths emigrated to the American states, their religious icons were welcomed into the Avengers.
Always in a position subservient to the national god of the American states, Captain America.
Explaining Thor's subservience to the other deity in 20th century myths.
This allowed America to exert control on the religion of new arrivals while still allowing them freedom of religion.
Critics of this theory typically point to a lack of evidence that Captain America was ever a central figure in the recruitment of most or any Avenger.
Some stories that describe the origin of the Pantheon even exclude him leading many historians to believe that Thor was considered an Avenger before Captain America was.
These theories, their strengths and their flaws, will be examined in greater detail over the course of this paper.
Alongside other less common answers to the burning questions about how Norse paganism survived and evolved over the centuries.